[SPEAKER_04]: Okay, so my question is about dukkha contemplation.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, like, I encountered that, like, if there is not enough faith, then this dukkha contemplation can kind of cause depression, sort of, because, like, when you consider that, like, I mean, death is inevitable, suffering is inevitable,
[SPEAKER_04]: And you don't know that there is a way out of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, maybe, like, even your practice is also futile.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, and basically, then, what you are, kind of, you are just stuck in suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, yeah, so, how to deal with this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think, see, the first question would be, like, why would you be contemplating dukkha in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: What's your motivation behind it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, as far as I understand, it's...
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, I think it kind of makes you sober about life.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, but I mean specifically you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when you contemplate dukkha, what's... why are you doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you expect to come from that contemplation as a practice?
[SPEAKER_04]: I would say I expect, like, some calmness and dispassion to come from it.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it is often, instead of this, it's coming a kind of some kind of despair or sort of... yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, see, I think that's already pretty much where the answer is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're doing it to get something from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to contemplate it to get the calmness, to get the dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, really, you want to contemplate it so to understand it on its own terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if no calmness comes, if no dispassion comes, which, by the way, it's impossible for it to not come, but if your motivating factor is, I want these things to come, that's why I contemplate this,
[SPEAKER_00]: That can kind of take the center stage too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, although theoretically, yes, you contemplate it, so to be dispassionate, but on the immediate level, your immediate motivation can be the reason why you're not getting what you're expecting to get.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the craving because of which you're contemplating that, is maintained because you're overlooking it and feeling justified in craving further of this contemplation until the peace and dispassion come.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're kind of blocking yourself, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_04]: But I'd say, in my case, it's even not quite like this, because it seems like this contemplation is running in my head on their own.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, eh... to...
[SPEAKER_04]: I know, it's almost automatically.
[SPEAKER_04]: It is because, eh...
[SPEAKER_04]: I noticed that in past, for instance, these things helped me to overcome, like, attachment to many things.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, to see, for instance, that work is not really, like, so much important, that, I don't know, like...
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, that's... again, like, even back then, all of those contemplations were infected with the craving, with the desire of wanting to get something from it.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it can work, relatively speaking, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, that craving can help you replace, you know, craving for family, partnership, work, career, to crave for forest, meditation, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the sooner or later, the time will come when that will be the impediment, the obstacle.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, given that, yes, you already have no desire for career, or work, or academic pursuits, or family, or partnerships, what you're left with now is
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that craving that has helped you overcome those, say, worldly attachments, coarser attachments, now it's just too coarse to address the subtler attachments.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what's too coarse?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that very craving that motivates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those expectations on account of contemplation, I expect peace and dispassion, but it's not coming.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just depression and despair.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because craving keeps that, as I said, polluted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you really want to, like, recalibrate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pretty much the context and the reasons for contemplating things in the first place and whereby...
[SPEAKER_00]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would I be fine if for the rest of my life I don't experience any peace nor any dispassion?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is that a problem for me?
[SPEAKER_00]: I still know what to do and what not to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: It still doesn't affect my choice to keep the precepts and choose wisely, even if I don't get any reward for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you want to present that idea and see whether your mind will be like, whoa, whoa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not a chance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, well, why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it could happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you lose your health or something and you won't be able to practice all these things that you deem practice to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: But internally, theoretically, you shouldn't be affected by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're practicing rightly, you shouldn't be affected by that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what you want to start showing to your own mind that, well, the time will come when we won't be able to manage or do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Will you be fine with that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I mean, like, you want to kind of refine your own motivation for practice, whereby... No, I contemplate dukkha, so... to understand it, and so that my mind gets used to it, that there is no resistance or depression in face of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a reward in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as of now, that reward is too subtle to be measured by the expectation of reward, of peace and dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why it feels insignificant.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, what should one kind of tell to the mind, tell to oneself, that it stops expecting this kind of
[SPEAKER_04]: I know, it's basically saying, okay, like, you're doing this, you're keeping precepts, or you're doing your meditation, your contemplation, or whatever else, but you still, you feel like you're still afraid of suffering, still afraid of death, of, like, I mean, let's say, on, like, sometimes mind presents some, like, violent scenarios, which are, kind of, disturbing, yeah, frightening, and, and you see, like,
[SPEAKER_04]: I know what to do with this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, again, for as long as... See, the mind can only go so far if your views don't support mind's expectations.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it feels as if, oh, well, my mind still expects, or my mind fears, or my mind does this, I must address it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all of that is enabled by your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: By what you still emphasize or deem important.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start rewriting your views, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: correcting them, then the mind can't go that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eventually, it will have to start to follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the views direct, they set up the direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if your mind is still expecting, it still means you, yourself, is a good chance, are also still expecting it on account of the views of the practice and what's important and what should come from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You haven't questioned that long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, and by the way, like, maybe part of your views might be quite okay, quite right, but the fact that they were never questioned, never brought to question and into uncertainty for a sufficient amount of time, they are wrong for that reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, even the right view, people can be holding it wrongly, which is why it won't be their right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you yourself have to be re-evaluating yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, okay, but am I also expecting things?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, contemplate enough to show you, until it sinks in, that those things shouldn't be expected, because they make no sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, even if the mind comes up with expectations, it's contained within the right perception that you developed, with more correct views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ask yourself, as I said, eh... Would you be fine?
[SPEAKER_00]: With uncomfortable things, not being able to practice, or be on a retreat, or be in a seclusion, or be sheltered from stuff, if you end up in an environment where those things are not accessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, in your imagination, is that affecting you?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it is, you realize, well, that's really the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already the first step towards solution.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just taking for granted that, yeah, yeah, I must follow this through, whereby I will get that environment, will get that practice, and never address the fact that it bothers me.
[SPEAKER_04]: And if I figure out that I'm bothered by it, so what's... Well, that's... Let's see.
[SPEAKER_00]: You figure out that you're bothered by it, and you recognize, okay, this is what needs to be addressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whenever the pressure comes up to follow that which bothers you, as in, like, to avoid it,
[SPEAKER_00]: To go away with it, it's like, well, actually, no, that would be fueling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you can, as I said, find a good enough balance in terms of environment, where you wouldn't be too precious or too, like, high maintenance, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, well, the first step of when you find it your bother is to not act out of the bother.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how the views that revolve around management of the bother, avoiding the bother,
[SPEAKER_00]: Finding the perfect environment where nothing will bother you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those views will then evaporate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, for maintenance of the views, the whole kind of... Well, the views would pretty much depend on mind jumping on things, left and right, management, this, avoidance, resistance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind jumping left and right, management, avoidance, resistance, depends on you enabling it through your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you start not following through with your actions, the mind will have to come down.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind comes down, the views would have to settle down.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't remain, the cloud of dust can't remain if there is nothing running up and down the road anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not like instantaneously kind of unplugging something, but it is like removing the supporting factor until it settles down.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what we say, like, it kind of boils down to recognizing the motivation for whatever aspect of the practice you think you're developing or you want to be developing, and then not taking that motivation for granted either, but recognizing, hold on, is this rooted in avoidance?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is this rooted in fear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, am I addressing fear or I'm just trying to not deal with it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And start, like, bringing it back home, basically, where you kind of know, I should not be...
[SPEAKER_00]: I should be able to not be moved by this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if my mind moves, I'm the one who should be able to not just act out and follow through with these pressures and compulsions and so on.
[SPEAKER_04]: So then, I'd say, the start here is to kind of stop trying to find some like perfect environment for practice and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: A hundred percent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And like, the sooner you stop that, the sooner you begin the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice that really matters towards actual liability to suffer and everything else, regardless of the circumstances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the very kind of... the nature of, say, consciously choosing to not follow the compulsion to manage or address the discomfort that arises, it's going to feel like a very strong confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why people don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what they justified trying, like, changing, and going further, and doing this, and doing that, and moving from here to there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if they stop, it feels like you're enclosed completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, like, no, no escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the beginning of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why, again, the precepts and everything is just to train the mind to enable you to be able to contain your mind when it faces that confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that confinement will come, as the Buddha described, the four mountains coming closer with every day.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nothing other than the confinement, until you're confined so much that you're destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sickness, aging, death are the unavoidable confinements, but the whole practice is to create the confinement of the right kind, so that the mind learns how to settle within, not to depend on action and management
[SPEAKER_00]: In order for its perception of its survival.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you want to do it before... You want to train your mind in regards to confinement before the confinement really comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, psychologically, it will feel the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for many people, just having to take on the precepts will feel like death, dying, fear, abyss, as the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sensuality is that freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Saying no to that feels like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, like you're buried into the ground alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's frightening, but only from the point of view of depending on the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might not have... say, you might have refined that, so you don't depend on the senses as much, because you've been restrained, living in the right environments, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you might well be managing... depending on management, on technique, or counteraction, when this happens and that, on movement within.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also a way of escaping confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha said, like in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, you have Samana and Brahmins that do take on restraint and start living withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then they hold on to the views and start arguing and falling out over views.
[SPEAKER_00]: People often think that it's like philosophical debates that they disagree with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the world is eternal.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, the world is not eternal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you, sir, don't know what you talk about and stuff like... No, views literally means
[SPEAKER_00]: Standpoints in regard to day-to-day life will become supercharged with importance once you withdraw yourself from centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Views that range, and everybody that lived in the monastery saw that, that range from, sure, is the world eternal or not, to the point of, how did you put your shoes when you came in here?
[SPEAKER_00]: In this monastery, we don't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, it's really important.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because confinement has come now, because you are not spilling out into the senses, so you're going to have different ways internally of compensating for that fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So these little things that other people do become very, very important and must be aligned rightly, because otherwise, I feel confined.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if I don't give in the first wave of compulsion to break out of that internal mental confinement of my citta, then I will give in to the second wave, or the third wave, because they're going to become more and more increasingly pressuring and irrational.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was the example many of us seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you know, the suttas clearly say you shouldn't say anything if it's rooted in irritation or anger, until your mind is in the right place, until you recognize that it's beneficial for everybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you would see that, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Something would come up in the community, and you could see the monkeys, like, super irritated, annoyed, threatened by it, even.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they might not say anything that immediate occasion, but the next occasion, they would have to say something, because in their mind, it's like the proliferation increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, oh, if I don't say like this, he'll do it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't stop and question, well, what if they do it for the rest of their life?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if everybody does the wrong thing for the rest of their life?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I endure that confinement of not getting my way?
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, they don't go that far.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, I might not say the first day, but then I'll think, oh, but he'll do it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if he does it, then he'll do it as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, she'll do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, everybody will do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, everything I worked for, the monastery I built, the tradition we preserved, all of it will go to ruin.
[SPEAKER_00]: Therefore, I have to say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: For the sake of the dhamma, for the sake of the monastery, for the sake...
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to say it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they then prioritize proliferated ideas of external importance and circumstances and ignore their own very intention that they're still annoyed and that's why they're saying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, like, you say no once to your mind, you might feel a bit of, like, a resistance, but it won't become increasingly or intensely irrational immediately, because, again, there is still hope that eventually you'll say it, and the mind will get its way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't say it again, and again, and again, the confinement, the perception of confinement, is increasing, and the animal is going to start complaining.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be quicker to be agitated, more irrational, more pressuring, more threatening.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's part of the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But once that starts happening, that's where people start to justify spilling out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they might not spill out as much as go back to the sensuality, but it will certainly spill out to the point of
[SPEAKER_00]: Arguing, carrying grudges, ill will on account of views and disagreements, and how things should be, and how things should run, and what you said, and what he meant, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of those are views on account of which samanas and brahmins stab each other with verbal daggers, as the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, oh, yeah, okay, so I shouldn't do that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I have withdrawn myself from sensuality, but now I have to withdraw myself from these standpoints.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by questioning them for myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: How is that going to feel?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly how it felt before.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna feel like your mind is now even more confined, because you're not allowing it quick escape, quick management, quick cover-up, quick kind of addressing of things, so that everything feel fine, feels fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And and that's that's actually a natural progression.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I say, like, you choose to restrain today, and then in five days time, there's still the same pressure to say something comes up, and you still restrain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you restrain to the point of there is no expiry date to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the mind keeps coming up for the rest of my life with this ridiculous, irrational, compulsion, pressure, for the rest of my life I will not intentionally allow it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the mind will get really, really upset with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now we're talking about, kind of, ultimate scenarios.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're taking away the hope that sooner or later you will give in, like how you used to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by the way, it doesn't need to be this kind of grandiose determinations of, I will never lay down or I shall never speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just these little things.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the, I don't know, the eyes want to look, the mouth wants to say something, you recognize it's unwholesome, you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it comes up again and again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And three months later, the same thing keeps coming up.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might be three days, it might be three months, it might be three years, because you don't know how deep the tendencies of citta go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are ready to train the animal, and if you are ready to train the animal, it doesn't matter to you how long you have to train it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be nice, sure, if it's not too long, but doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not concerned with the length, you're concerned with the quality of each and every session, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what preferences your citta have, well, that can... and how deep they go, well, that can only become apparent as you start training it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sometimes people would think, well, surely, two months later, I shouldn't be thinking about this same pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like, why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you thinking it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Are you choosing to think it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, not really.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do you then expect to not be thinking about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that also up to you to decide?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if for two years later my mind is pressuring me with same stuff, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was never... the practice was never about changing what mind thinks about.
[SPEAKER_00]: The practice was not crossing the line when those things want to push you over.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the mind... what the mind thinks about are not the things that want to cross the line in terms of unbeneficial behavior, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you also recognize kind of where your responsibility is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not spilling into sensuality, not spilling into coarse act by body and speech, and then, yeah, not finding the escape from that confinement in views and standpoints and ideas of how things should be and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when the mind does come up with those expectations, you recognize the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, I have to endure this now and not fuel it and not take it for granted and, okay, yeah, yeah, yeah, let's find a solution, let's sort it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it a problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why does anything, like, anything that mind comes up with, why do I have to do anything about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I have to move?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I have to figure it out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I... Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, why can't I just not do anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you choose to do not do anything, and then the mind becomes even more threatening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not always, but it can happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, okay, well, surely that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not my doing or not doing of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the fact that if the mind is not getting what it wants, when it wants it, it turns... it's turning against me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pressuring me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's threatening me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the one like, oh...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, that's... that's not a beneficial arrangement.
[SPEAKER_00]: That the mind pressures you into decisions, into action, that you choose to give in because the pressure is too much.
[SPEAKER_04]: But when, like, the doubt comes then, like, actually, mind starts saying, like, basically, it's there, kind of, you started this, because you thought that this can help you to, like, to overcome suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you could say, this is, this was craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: But the mind starts saying, okay, you, you are going this way, maybe, like, I don't know, ten years or whatever, how many years, and you're still kind of like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I mean, yeah, that's, that's a valid thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a valid thing for a mind to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you should expect results.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then you kind of say, maybe this, like, maybe it doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe... Or maybe you've been doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Maybe I've been doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, you start thinking, like, maybe I'm incapable of this.
[SPEAKER_04]: Maybe it's just wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or maybe, like... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a difference between, like, questioning it to an objective degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, well, yeah, I've been doing this for 10 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know...
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have anything to show for, but then there is a difference between that and when you cross that line and go into, well, maybe you are just hopeless, maybe you don't know what you're doing, maybe...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no, the possibility for enlightenment remains undiminished for as long as you're alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even this is questionable, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Possibility is something...
[SPEAKER_00]: It is possible that you can free yourself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes, my doubt... Well, of course, of course, but that's, that's the, like... To a degree, you have to doubt things, including your own practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you recognize the doubt, now, to be revolving around, like, a compulsive core, that's when you have to endure it instead.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the difference between, like, the doubt as a hindrance and the overall doubt in, like, what freedom from suffering is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because doubt is a hindrance, is a habit of the mind to pressure you to clarify things that are uncertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's something you actually have to not give in to and habitually fuel it for the solution.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the mind starts doubting, oh, well, is it even possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, okay, that's a valid question.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you stop there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it even possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I don't know, but I hope it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that certainly doesn't allow you to... oh, yeah, you're worthless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, where did that come from?
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you know that that's the case?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might think like, oh, I'm nowhere near close to enlightenment, but how do you know that you are further away from it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know that either.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize the objective uncertainty about it, but you have to be careful as to how much you allow it, that compulsion, to be fed through your own seeking for the solution.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, basically, when the doubt comes up as a hindrance, like repetitively, in that compulsive sense, it's not really about the answer.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about getting rid of the discomfort of that experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're seeking the answer, seemingly, to clarify the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: In reality, you're seeking the answer so that the mind can escape the confinement of this uncomfortable feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you don't forget the doubt is unpleasant, and then make the effort to not act out of that displeasure, you are containing the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more you do it, like...
[SPEAKER_00]: The more irrational it will become.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more irrational it becomes, it will show you more and more how ridiculous the mind is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it was the power of compulsion that will always get you back in.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then become concerned with A's and B's and C's as the answers and all this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in reality, it was always remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Confinement of discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can't bear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Act out and then spend days and days trying to resolve something until the feeling is appeased.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's basically inadvertently fueling the doubt that you're trying to resolve.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if sometimes that doubt can have, as I said, a legitimate basis, such as, well, I've been doing this for 10 years, am I free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's a valid reflection.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now, in the compulsion of that discomfort, see, recognizing that, oh, maybe I'm...
[SPEAKER_00]: I was wrong, is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, the doubt comes on top of that, amplifies that discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you stay with it, and not fuel that kind of mental proliferation account without?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you think, I must find a solution, while in reality, you're really just trying to avoid that very discomfort?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, I think I would like to find a solution, but it feels like there's no solution, indeed, because I know
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you don't need to...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, obviously, you can't know that there is liberation unless you're on path to be liberated yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So... but then my point is, if you feel like you're losing faith, well, my point is that you also can't not... well, you can't know that there is no liberation either.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the equal footing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you want it or not, you are left in the state of a liberation, could be possible, and you have nothing to lose by trying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because your life is objectively better, by not pursuing career, family, worldly craving, money, partnerships, relationships, entanglement, burden, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, okay, I...
[SPEAKER_00]: I have a crisis of faith.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know if it's possible, but I also don't know if it's not possible either.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, I might as well continue doing what I can have, and intelligent recognition is beneficial for me, and carries the possibility of actually freeing me from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But at the same time, yes, you obviously need to develop some shift or some upgrade, if it's been 10 or more years, and you're still not free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just indefinitely, well, it will come when it comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Surely, in 10 years' time, if things were being done rightly, it should have come.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it should have been developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, that's the unpleasant part.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel like you might have to start all over again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you might have to undo what you thought you've built.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the doubt comes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: But instead of taking it on, and not losing perspective, people then want to manage the doubt, one way or the other, to avoid the discomfort that it revealed.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the good thing is, like, if you start practicing rightly, you don't have to wait for 10 years to get the results.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even if somebody, say, wasted 50 years of not getting anywhere, not getting anything from the practice, if then they start rightly, they can get it right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, from that point of view, nothing's been wasted, even the wrong effort, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: In hindsight, can all be made right, if things are actually then done rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But until then, a person has to stop running away from confinement, internal confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that happens all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in most of the monasteries, I remember, it was like monks are constantly moving from one place to the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: When things become, like, too close, too confining, too this, too that, go to the next place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go and find another ājā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go and find another one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I met marks of doing that for like 12, 13 years, 15 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: And eventually, you get tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be constantly moving or trying to outrun the confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the only other option was left.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dismiss the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, disrobe, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop practicing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... Again, all of that is the same attitude that's been maintained from the day one.
[SPEAKER_00]: When things got too confining, I gave in and allowed the mind to run away through doing this or that and going there and justifying management and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you might kind of have to if it's too much, but you don't need to lie to yourself about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to justify it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, it's too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: This monastery is just too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't bear it here.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too strict.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too this, it's too that.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is overwhelming me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I need to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: I want to go somewhere else when it's a bit easier.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, a person might do that, but they can still do it authentically, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can recognize, okay, I'm not ready for this level of confinement, so I'll lower it down a bit, but
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no need to lie to yourself and present that as some sort of practice and say, oh, you can't practice here, nobody knows what they're doing here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if that were true, none of that should be your personal problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people use that, finding faults and stuff, so to justify them running out of the confinement that their mind started perceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until the novelty of the new place runs out, and it starts to feel stale and confining again, and then again a new place, and a new place, and a new place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And ironically enough, then people become... monks become even more sensitive, and disturbed, more easily disturbed, by sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, than they were before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the more you're trying to outrun the confinement, the bigger it gets.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means the faster you need to run.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means the quicker you'll be reminded of the stuff that you're trying to outrun.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, they speak too loudly here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the smell here is too bad.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the food is like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's too many people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's too little people.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's too high.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too low.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too wet.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's too dry.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always gonna be something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't look past that and see where is my intention rooted in wanting to do this or that, move or say, and it's like, oh,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's obviously rooted in compulsion, in pressure, in mind trying to get me to to release it back into the wilderness, to some extent, to ease, to allow it some sort of relief.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: And wherever I go, I'll carry that problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll carry that attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no place will be perfect.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can live with a hundred arahants, Buddha himself, and that person would still find fault with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because all of that's done just to
[SPEAKER_00]: Compensate the responsibility for the confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was that whole, like, Ajahn Chah, that funny story of monks go around the monastery, whichever monastery they're in, they complain about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said it's like going around from a place to place carrying shit in your shoulder bag.
[SPEAKER_00]: And wherever you get to, you complain that that place smells of shit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you brought it with yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, that's like... accepting of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't do anything else ever in your life, just accepting that the value of not running away from the confinement imposed by the precepts restrained withdrawal, that's already a massive step in the right direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because again, it's gonna be... the mind will not be indifferent towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a very strong kind of habit and force.
[SPEAKER_00]: They get people to move, or avoid, or compensate, or manage, or...
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop the views as means of coping with that confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to keep reminding yourself to stay with it, to not fuel it, to not blindly follow it.
[SPEAKER_00]: How long?
[SPEAKER_00]: Depends on how wild the mind was.
[SPEAKER_00]: How wild you allow it... allowed it to be in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, sooner or later, it will have to sit down.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same, again, simile of the elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the suttas, you trap it from the wilderness.
[SPEAKER_00]: I actually saw a video of the ancient Indian technique of taming the elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was like what the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get... you separate this elephant, you get them into this enclosure of this massive post and stuff, and they go feral.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're mental.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're trying to break, destroy, like absolute kind of rabbit panic.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then they calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: They urinate, defecate, scream, but then there is like... the wall's too strong and then they calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no other choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind is contained.
[SPEAKER_00]: When it calms down, then the monk kind of offers the next step of training, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or like the trainer for the elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You confine it and you have to wait for it until it sits on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Till it calms down, and then you offer it some food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: As it's clear to you now, we are not spilling out into the old ways that you are pressuring me to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you're happy, we can do stuff within this new perimeter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if the mind says, no, get away, I'll kill you, then, okay, you wait there longer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the part of the simile where the trainer comes and offers some food and water to the elephant that has calmed down because it exhausted itself,
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still wild.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, okay, I'll come back later.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it comes back later.
[SPEAKER_00]: Eventually, the elephant will accept it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when it accepts it, it's like, okay, now we speak on my terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I think one of the... probably the entire, you know, what I always sort of have a bone to pick, the commentary, the contemporary views, the meditation techniques, the management, the worst thing of why all those things are so unbeneficial,
[SPEAKER_00]: is because they kind of enable people to believe that they can start the training of the mind without the prior confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without having the mind settle down after the panic existential threat confined by the actual precepts being trained in, not giving in to the unbeneficial behavior, and then not running away from the confinement either, until you see your mind sit down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all these contemporary practices enable people to believe that they can practice without doing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although, as I said, it doesn't take great kind of study of the suttas to discover that that is absolutely necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like the first step.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people will think, yeah, I know, I know, I'm doing it bit by bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the meantime, the real practice is this or that, that, and I'm getting closer to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just sort of believing that, yeah, look, the mind is listening, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind just happened to be wanting to walk in the same direction that you are going.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, quickly you'll find out that it's not in your control when that direction changes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or when something else comes in the way and changes it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, ironically enough, the practice of training the mind on account of the right confinement,
[SPEAKER_00]: Get swapped for managing the mind and allowing it to perpetually, sort of, escape the confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't go back to centrality, but I go back to this technique, to that teaching, to this place, to this place, move the monastery, move that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, you... as I said, a person might not have been as, kind of, behaving coarsely about it, because they do keep the precepts, but now everything else they've done in the name of practice is actually rooted in avoiding confinement internally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why, like, they don't start practicing even 50 years later.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it always remains perpetually available right there in your face.
Did you say something?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, it is like running away from suffering.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I would like to know what suffering is.
[SPEAKER_02]: Is it possible?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's what suffering... that's where suffering comes from.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes from the... from the citta that has no diminished cravings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you don't see that presence of dukkha,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because of the presence of craving in your citta.
[SPEAKER_02]: It is a raging elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might not even be that raging.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, maybe you have kept the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe you don't have strong desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, different people have different preferences and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact is, you haven't made a connection that presence of craving inside of the animal, inside of the mind, means presence for suffering for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you get what you want or not, becomes irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simply,
[SPEAKER_00]: The attitude of craving, in that elephant, is felt as suffering in you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why you want to train the mind to stop craving, so that you are free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for as long as you don't see that, your suffering will be attributed to, oh, because he said something, or I didn't get what I want, or I got too much of what I didn't want, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But those things are indirect,
[SPEAKER_00]: Causes, so to speak, not even causes, they're indirect circumstances, because of which the animal chooses to react this way or that way, and you not see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not seeing that, you are the one suffering on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, like, the prerequisite for sotāpatti is seeing the animal, seeing the citta, to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where the craving is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you are not doing the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just inadvertently enabling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also why you can't just stop, or just stop the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just let go and stop the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just switch it off.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You gotta confine the animal so that it cannot proliferate that craving further.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it needs to calm down within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you dictate, as I said, you know, the beneficial behavior, the eightfold path, everything that, you know, the wholesome thoughts, not unwholesome, the right perceptions, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that craving of that animal, the urges, the compulsion, the pressure, become more and more apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more apparent it is, the clearer it becomes to you that that's the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of that is freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the path to fulfill that is the path of confining it rightly until it sees for itself.
[SPEAKER_02]: And this contemplations of things, it is like food for this elephant.
[SPEAKER_02]: When it is calmed down...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, yeah, same, like, well, you're familiar with the dog, so it's like, you know, you try to give a command to a dog that, that's not giving you attention, it's not gonna work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first you have to get its attention, and then give it a command, and then it responds.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the mind is not confined enough, has not settled down in that confinement without you allowing it to spill out, because it was too much, because of your views took you in the directions and ideas that you know are rooted in compulsion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if the mind is not calmed down enough, you giving perception, it's like shouting at a dog that not even see you, because it's so occupied with something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first you need to make it clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are here with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: The world that you like, the wilderness that you depend on, is no more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why I say to people, like, even if you spend next 50 years trying to keep the eight precepts, and failing every second day, but each time you take it up, you take it in an infinite sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are actually practicing more than somebody who keeps them for the rest of their life, but never really takes it on mentally, that for the rest of their life they will never engage with this.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just circumstantially remain unengaged, but living off the pleasure of the possibility that they could escape the confinement if they want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be infinite, even if you fail.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, because this is talking through... Because that's what, exactly, that's what speaks to the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you start deciding or determining on the level of those possibilities of escape that the mind can find the joy in,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where the mind starts to listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's just circumstantial, yes, no, I abstain this, I don't know, for how long?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, okay, so the mind still lives off hope that, well, sooner or later, I can go back to those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, oh, it has to be other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's completely upside down.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, even, as I said, even if you successfully manage to keep the precepts only for like one week,
[SPEAKER_00]: If, when you decided to keep it with the idea was, oh, for the rest of my life, mind will not go back to this, that one week can be a lot more beneficial than, as I say, seven months of just keeping the precepts because you're in the environment when there is nothing challenging you and not many temptations.
[SPEAKER_00]: But never take it on in that, like, mental sense, like, no, no, no, I am confining you within this new norm of behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, if it's not indefinite, then the mind is like, sure, sure, sure, I'll listen to you until you let me out and then we're back onto, you know, what I used to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: How do you balance that with, like, realism?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, maybe not the precepts, but, for example, if you tell yourself, whenever the mind is lazy, like this reflection you were talking about, if you see your mind being lazy, you just do the thing that it's being lazy in regards to.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can kind of take that on, but how would you do it in the permanent sense, if you just... if there's just kind of the realistic sense of knowing
[SPEAKER_01]: That it will take several iterations of taking it on for it to stick.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, trial and error.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you shouldn't really... you shouldn't surrender to that, like, oh, I'll do it and then we'll see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, because that already kind of dilutes the quality of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already, like, half committed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it takes a bit more effort to re-establish it when you know that you've...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see,
[SPEAKER_00]: Through re-establishing it, the level where those determinations and decisions and choices should be made becomes clearer and clearer.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can find that spot, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Quicker and quicker.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or more accurately, so to speak, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it does always come down to... Again, none of these unbeneficial things can happen on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're always rooted in your choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's like, you are the one who chooses to release the elephant.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to let it go too far, to allow, to cover up, to pretend that it's not confined and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you could just abstain from that choice and maintain the practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to keep doing anything new.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why everything boils down to, you know, what we often say in the talks,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you know, you have the broad precepts, the kind of coarse behavior, kind of not giving in to that, but then the time comes when you recognize, am I acting out of pressure and do I feel justified in doing so?
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, am I acting out of compulsion and do I feel justified in doing so?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, I am giving in
[SPEAKER_00]: To the degree that's still present in the... to the degree of wilderness that's still present in that elephant, and I'm giving in to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for as long as there is compulsion of any kind, craving of any kind, I can't say I'm free.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, have I been inadvertently maintaining that craving through my views of what should be done in the name of practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: While in reality, I was just acting out of compulsion and avoiding confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where the questioning comes in.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, why do I need to do anything?
[SPEAKER_00]: When the pressure arises to act, hold on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I accept it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do I want to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Can I just not do either and stay with it for as long as it wants to stay?
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if I hope, I hope it goes away soon, I still choose to stay with it and not make it go away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because having to do anything on account of
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything is a form of burden.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what if you can't do what you think you're supposed to, or what you perceive there's the way out?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if you can't do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't then say, oh, I'm free.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm imperturbable.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm burdenless.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm untouched, like a lotus above the water, if I still have to do something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means I'm not... my mind is not calm enough or trained well enough in regard to the confinement, whereby
[SPEAKER_00]: It can sit and take it, like the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: The elephant getting it ready for the battle.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not being pronged with sticks and spears and hit.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it's still kind of shy, it pulls away, hides its trunk.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, it's not ready.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ready when it doesn't move.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it doesn't need to move.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the only way to find that out is if you stop enabling it to move.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think it's challenging when it starts accumulating, like with practicing, this comes, this comes, and then it just kind of goes on and then at one point you're just overwhelmed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But then it's again just... Then you restart.
[SPEAKER_00]: And each time you restart rightly,
[SPEAKER_00]: Being overwhelmed will be put in a better perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter how many moving parts there are, the framework of the feeling remains the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether it's one thing that's uncomfortable, or a thousand things uncomfortable, you know that discomfort is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the satipaṭṭhāna, correctly done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of this, from left I go to right, and do that, and when it's this, I press this, like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know pleasant feeling is pleasant feeling, unpleasant is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whichever feeling is there, I know that's what's felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if it's big or small, multiple, individual.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with the state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter why and how and how many times and how long.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says he knows the mind of lust as mind of lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need more information.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need more specific details.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind of anger is mind of anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter if it's a little bit irritation or a big anger.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind of anger is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Animal is angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all I need to know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Depressed mind as depressed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not depressed mind, but then you undepress it through doing this and that.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing it for what it is, is how you basically set it up rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, depressed mind is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind of lust is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind of anger is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: You not seeing it as such, that's where the problem is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and you don't see it because you keep giving in to the pressure and compulsion of tendency to just change it this one time and then I'll stop doing, I promise.
[SPEAKER_03]: One thing I was thinking about the feeling, like there are three types of feelings, and me not being over the shore yet, means I have craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not being over what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Over the river, on the other side, right?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, craving is always present, and craving, it's always felt unpleasantly, because it's... Well, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If a person's honest enough to admit that, and not just perpetually
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of maintain the delusion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what I was thinking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is then, everything that it feels pleasantly, actually not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, it's kind of... Well, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Twisted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because of this... Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, like, when you get the elephant in the enclosure or the dog, everything he wants to do is for the sake of getting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why there is no other way around or a magical solution other than
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to keep it in that setup, in that internal confinement, until it calms down within that, and accepts that as the new environment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can allow it to move, to do this or that, within that space, that's not concerned with escaping anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's when you start to recognize the difference between intentions that are free from craving, and intentions that are not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And intentions that are not, are the ones that are concerned with escape.
[SPEAKER_00]: Escaping the confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the intention is not about escaping confinement, then it's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for as long as the dog wants to escape, well, you keep it on a leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wants to jump the fence, wants to dig under it, you keep it on a leash.
[SPEAKER_00]: When he comes down and stops doing that, you don't have to keep it, like, next to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can let it go, let it run, let it play, because it's not concerned with escaping anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, sure, you can refine that as well now,
[SPEAKER_00]: That further training, but that will be self-evident, how to do it, if you would have overcome the general kind of tendency of the mind to want to escape all the way.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that's the thing, if I...
[SPEAKER_03]: I cannot know pleasant feeling because I have none.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you do.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean you have none?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I keep having craving for... Well, yes, but again, craving is not the cause of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Craving is in regard to feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, everything you feel gets distorted through craving, but that doesn't mean that you don't know what pleasure or agreeability is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just don't know how to experience it apart from craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And think about, again, same similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do have an animal enclosed, but still, what is on its mind, what is on your mind's mind, is to escape, to escape the confinement.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within that confinement, it can find agreeable things, but it won't appreciate them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's still concerned with more important thing to escape, because it still has a hope of escaping, because it still thinks that you will let it out eventually, maybe yourself are not clear, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when it accepts that, that there is no escape from this confinement, and it calms down, then, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there is that joyful thing that I remember from before, I just paid no attention to it, because, again, my concerns were of a different kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, you know, the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: People can relate to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, they're saying, oh, you don't know how good you had it until you lose it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, things you take for granted, things you look past, things you think is irrelevant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Give me that, give me that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Buddha says, like, develop pleasure of renunciation to abandon the pleasure of non-renunciation, the pleasure of non-confinement and spilling out into the sense world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same, develop the pains of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to replace the pains of the world, the sensuality, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're factually better pains, pains of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, pains that you experience on account of rightly set up confinement, will make you overcome the pains of the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, these pains will be easily understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they are not manifold, overwhelming, deceiving and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the animal is contained and it's actually now there is a communication between you two, as opposed to open the gate and... you hope it might come back in three days, for a minute.
[SPEAKER_00]: And generally just run on autopilot, in regard to wants, likes, dislikes, pressures, hindrances and stuff.
Yes.